we're waiting for geshe michael
he uh he was very um
sad to hear this news so he he acted
quickly and he wanted to organize this
this webinar for us all
so we want to the format that we're
going to use
is we're going to have 30 minutes
uh a quick class that he's going to give
for us and the other 30 minutes he's
going to do q a
so please uh make sure that you post
your questions in the q a chat
and
we should be getting this michael very
soon
thank you very much
okay the floor is yours thank you for
coming
wait you're not okay
all right good
oh sorry we just we talked we were
talking about the format that we're
going to do
before you arrive that we're going to do
half an hour
classic
and then the other half an hour q a
okay good good okay good
can you hear me okay
yep
okay good good
all right uh good morning everybody
so i i i guess we all feel the same i i
feel very uh
nervous and
afraid and i feel upset
and
i also i start feeling angry
a little bit
at the big people you know
and
uh
and then i'm trying to keep my practice
you know and i'm trying to uh remember
all of the
things i learned and all of the things
that i teach and and i'm trying to
use them and i think
the the big thing
for me
right now is to try to remember
uh to use what i learned and
it's funny you know we are talking about
uh
the two husbands in the kitchen
almost every day and grandpa died
i'm talking about it abuelo right
i'm talking about it uh almost every day
and then uh i'm like you guys you know
when uh
when something happens then i i forget
everything
and uh i get upset or
i get angry
or afraid and uh
so
i think and and i couldn't sleep last
night and and uh
i'm thinking uh
for me
what i would like to do
is uh
i
i took three or four
little pieces of uh
things that i wrote in the last
20 years
that i think uh they talk about this
problem that we now have
and uh
so i thought uh like seiji said
uh we could do we could do like half an
hour i'd like to
review those uh
those old teachings with you guys
and it's not just for you it's for me
also
you know uh i need it also
and so i thought i would go through the
the old uh teachings about it for half
an hour
and then uh
after that i'd like to open it up for
question and answer
uh
and i i don't think it's so much a
teaching today but i think it's just uh
people who care about uh
compassion and we care about uh people's
we care about other people and
i think it's mostly just a reason for us
to get together
and support each other
from all countries
so i feel like we are
a big family
and uh we love each other very much and
i think nothing will change this
and uh
and we when
when we have trouble like this we have
to
uh
meet the family has to meet together
you know like when your
birth family had trouble your parents we
used to
sit everybody down at the table and
talk about things and
then
everybody feels a little bit more
centered
and we remember our mission we remember
uh
we remember
why
we have all these organizations and all
ssc yesterday somebody told me gesla
you look exhausted but uh we feel more
exhausted because uh you're teaching too
many classes you know
and
and uh
i think
i was like yeah i know it's like that
but uh
but now comes the time right in every
person's life comes a time
that we have to use what we learned
right in
and i think uh
in these
hard times
uh
we we have to use what we learned
and all of the classes all of the
translations
all of the ancient books uh
it's all for this you know it's all for
this
uh so
it's like a military training you know
so we are training training training
training and and now
today the war came and now we have to
use uh
what we learn you know so
uh
so i'm gonna just uh go through
this little reading i sent down so i i
i put together uh a reading
about old uh
some old things i wrote about this
questions and uh i'll go through them
for about half an hour
and
then let's just talk like family and
talk about how we can
help
the situation and how we can help each
other
and i think especially how we can help
to remember
our practice and remember what we
learned
and this is the time to use it and
it's kind of a warm up for dying you
know
like
this is a very
dangerous
and difficult time for many of our
friends
then other people like me we are sitting
at home
uh
my most difficult thing is to choose
which green drink i'm going to have this
morning and
you know i feel far away from the
problem
but actually this same problem will come
to all of us right
in time
uh
nobody's free from these problems the
problem will come
to my house
and
especially when i when i reach my death
i have to
understand these
things i have to use them
okay so i'm gonna share my screen
nah
i think i'll just read it straight uh
let me see
let me go get it oh and then sanji uh
after about half an hour maybe you can
choose some of the questions to answer
right ana ili i was thinking one hour
uh so we do a half hour
grandpa
talk and then half an hour we do some
questions yeah and seiji if you can
choose the questions from
yeah we have a lot of questions all
right
yeah
and uh usually grandpa talks too much in
the answer
and i'll try to uh
i'll try to actually answer the question
quickly okay
so let me get my uh
let me get up
yeah uh so i
first of all well i have
four different readings
that uh i chose for this uh problem
and if you don't have a copy i think
it's been translated into russian and
other languages and
if you
didn't get a copy
then um
just ask um like uh maria anton or inna
and you can get a copy so that the first
part
uh
i don't know 22 years ago
i was
i i remember i was living at the
mongolian uh temple small
mongolian monastery and um
i used to go in the temple by myself at
night
and i would write uh
i would write down some ideas i had for
a little book you know
and the book was called the garden
and
and it was a very beautiful time in my
life i was mostly alone
and
i was in the monastery and at night
uh it was very quiet and uh
i could sit in the temple was empty and
and i would just uh sit and
think about this garden
and you know the story of the garden is
uh there's
a young man and he meets a young lady in
the garden and then
[Music]
he uh
by the way let me show you a picture
on my i'll show you from my wall
[Music]
uh so that's the garden picture
uh this painting was made for me by a
mongolian
painter this is the original
from mineral paints paints
made in mongolia and
so it's a story about a young man and a
girl and
in a garden
and uh
he talks to different the young man
talks to different uh
masters
and he asks them questions in the story
and one of the questions is uh
you know
uh
i'll read you the questions okay so
uh they're talking about uh some kind of
way of thinking
that hurts all of us that hurts
everybody
and uh
the young man is asking a question to in
the story
the buddhist master named gunnar prabha
he comes to the garden
and they start talking
and
the young man has a question
and if you know guna prabha he wrote the
denia sutra
so the young man gets to ask a question
to gunnar prabha
and
first they talk about
uh problems with the soil
with the earth so in some parts of the
world like i i lived in india
uh i i used to go there a lot and um
there's something wrong with the soil
there that the soil is
used for so many thousand years
that uh it's very difficult to grow uh
crops there you know
even you take the seed a good seed
and you try to grow it in in in parts of
india
uh this the
dirt is tired
you know people have been planting the
same
things for thousands of years
and
and actually the dirt doesn't grow the
the crops don't grow very well
and so the young man asked the uh
this uh vinaya master
you know
what what's the
cause for this
change
in the earth in the soil
and then the master says well of course
it's uh because they they were
taking life taking the life of animals
and taking the life of people
in that country the people living there
and then
because they took the life of other
people
it changed the
the soil in their country
and it won't grow very well you see
uh things won't grow there very well uh
because of taking life before
and then uh
because of that answer
the young man
he's like
he starts to think about something else
you know
and he says
then is it true
that people can plant seeds together
if all the country if all the people in
one country
can plant the seeds to have a
bad soil the soil gets tired
then is it are you saying that it's
possible for people to plant seeds
together yeah
and uh
and the other
the teacher says yes
uh people from all countries can plant
seeds together
and
and that's what makes the borders
between countries
you know and the young man's a little
confused you think oh
the borders between countries
those are political borders those are
created by uh
by politicians or or by by generals you
know these are not created by
by the people in the country and the
teacher says no no uh
you know you have to go stand on the
border i used to go stand on the border
between mexico and america
just for fun i put one foot in america
and i put one foot in mexico and i tried
to feel
is there a difference in the dirt or or
is where's the line
i couldn't see the line
in we think that the line was drawn by
uh politics or
or or some war
but actually the line was drawn by seeds
right
uh
the border between countries
is drawn
by the seeds
of the people on each side and after
this program i have to go to peachtree
cafe
and
we are filming
uh
a new series
about how to eat well
and it will be part of ysi and part of
prana move
uh
and
the main idea of the shows people have
too much food
and they have to try not to eat so much
you know
and we have a whole tv show about it
how to eat healthy
if you have a lot of money
and then uh
i don't know two hours from here three
hours from here
there's many people who don't have any
food
can't get food
and
who made the border
uh between them you see uh
and then the young man in the garden he
asked a question you know uh
are you saying that if uh two countries
go to war
you know
then
if the soldiers of one country
killed the people in another country or
both ways
then there's does everybody in the
country get a seat
and
the vinaya master says yes
everybody gets to see everybody in the
country
you support the killing uh you get the
seat
uh even if you are not a soldier but uh
in my case i pay taxes i i pay taxes
in many countries i actually paid taxes
in ukraine and russia also
so
you know
uh
in a way
uh i'm supporting
uh
two different armies and and the
american army so i'm supporting many
armies so then they say well
did you gesture are you making seeds
uh
are you making seeds to have violence in
your life and
the main answer is then
if you
in your heart
if you don't support hurting other
people
if strongly in your heart if you don't
support hurting
other people and animals you don't make
a scene okay you do not make a scene
and if you try
peacefully
to
to stop violence uh
and to start with yourself right i mean
that's the
the main thing we have to talk about
today
is uh you know the violence that we see
in the kitchen
uh
the big thing we have to remember
is it's coming from me
you know it's always coming from me
i cannot blame
other people
and it's uh
foolish to hate other people in fact
if you understand the seeds
it's impossible to hate another
country's people it's not possible
and
and that's the whole idea
of learning
these teachings
if i
understand seeds
then i understand that the violence i
see is coming from me in the kitchen
and also in the country you know so uh
and fixing
the violence
uh it doesn't come from uh forcing
someone to stop violence oftentimes that
becomes violence also
to force other people the
the way to change the violence
is to fix the seeds in myself
and and two kinds of seeds right one is
uh
you know i
i must have done violence in the past
you know and violence doesn't have to be
shooting somebody
uh violence can be just
getting angry at somebody in your family
or getting angry at somebody in your job
and trying to hurt them and then because
the seeds
double every day
it's possible that the small violence in
our family or a job uh
it will grow into big violence so really
i have to
try to think about the violence i i did
in my family or my job
uh to my friends in the past
and then secondly i have to try to
make a dedication to this war
i have to dedicate my good seeds
you know and that means i have to try
very very hard
in this next few months i have to try
to stop being
violent in small ways to
my friends my family
people i live with people i work with
and and i have to try very hard to stop
the violence in my own heart and
and the big violence is coming from that
so anyway uh
in the garden book
the question is about self-defense you
know
if my country's attacked
uh by another country
you know uh
can i kill the people who are attacking
my family or my country cannot kill them
is it okay to kill them
and the answer is that this is another
turning at the wheel then the wheel will
turn again you know i i will kill
uh
the attacker
to protect my family and then uh
i will plant the seed again
to be attacked in the
future and and then i will kill again
and there's no end to it that's why
that's why the wheel of life is the
wheel you know and and we don't think
about it much but
[Music]
responding to violence with violence
is and responding to violence with
hatred uh
it it just creates more will the wheel
just continues you know
oh geshla then should i do nothing
should i just let people hurt me you
know and no that's not
the case either we're gonna talk about
it um
the next uh reading
uh that i sent you guys it's from uh dci
level 10
which is about anger
and
it's live tool inside that level it's
called my mom my mother with a knife you
know
and this comes from a true story
uh veronica's mother uh
we were uh
tried to help her in the nursing home
we used to go pretty often uh she died
in august but before that uh for
20 years we were taking care of her
and
so she
she was had a problem with her medicines
she would
take too much medicine by accident she
forgot
uh if she took it already today and
even we put the medicine in a box
and we put the date on the box still she
would take the wrong she'd take it two
times or three times
and then she'd get a little bit crazy
you know
and then sometimes uh you can imagine
if your mom took her
if she's 90 years old and
she took the
wrong medicine she took too much
and then she gets a little bit crazy
and this in the story in dci level 10
the
old lady
takes too much medicine she gets a
little bit crazy
then her daughter like veronica or me uh
we
we come to visit her
and she hears the
the door opening you know and somebody
has the key
and she's cooking something
and she she's because she took the
medicine too much
she's a little bit crazy and she
she thinks uh somebody's coming in the
house to murder her
so she grabs a knife
a big uh stigma and she
she comes to the
the door
to to defend herself you know
and then uh
you open the door
and your own mother come at you
with a knife you know
and
then what are you supposed to do you
know if it's your own mother
what's the right thing to do
and it's not the right thing to do to
stand there
and let your mother
stab you and kill you that's that's not
helpful also she will make bad seats
but also if it's my mom
you know i'm not gonna shoot her
or i'm not going to
kill her i will try to
help her
to to not do violence
so i don't know i i imagine with my mom
i will grab her around the waist or i
will
fall down i will try to take the knife
out of her hands
[Music]
even if she cuts me a little bit uh
it's okay i i i wouldn't kill her you
know i would try to
stop her peacefully or or try to
do anything i can do
uh without violence to to stop her so
it's not wrong to
defend yourself it's not wrong to
to try to stop people from doing
violence uh
but
but if we
try to kill a person
who's trying to kill us then then i
think we are almost the same
as this person that i
and if
if there was our mom
uh i don't think we would kill them i
think we would be killed first before we
will kill the mom so
that's the second reading i put in the
and you you can read the whole thing
it's kind of long uh it's been
translated into many languages the third
part of this uh
letter i sent you guys it's about the
two husbands in the kitchen
and that's just you know
it's the whole story
and
we come home
to the kitchen we're tired
we worked hard
we bought the groceries we picked up the
kids
we spent the whole day making money for
the family
and we're tired
and we're thinking we're hoping we can
come home
and my husband or my wife will will just
look at me and say oh honey you look so
tired and thank you for
buying the groceries thank you for
taking care of the kids you know thank
you for
working and making money for us and you
know welcome home
and they give you a big hug and
you know maybe they cook dinner for you
and instead of that
you come in the kitchen and they and
they they yell at you for no reason
they just say oh
you're such an idiot you know
and then
you feel so terrible you know you feel
so bad
uh someone's attacking you and and you
didn't do anything
and then then
you guys know the story
uh we have to remember
that we we
we cost it we planted the seeds
and if we think about it
for even a short time we can understand
that uh
we can understand that this is coming
from me but maybe i yelled at my kids
you know lost me we can't find
the small seed
that grew into a big tree we can find it
if we look we can find it
and then we just have to try to stop it
it's too late to stop it in the kitchen
once the seed opens
nobody in the universe
there's nobody buddha god nobody
can put the tree back in the sea it's
not possible
it won't happen
all we can do is
try to
change our
future behavior
and try to make a problem
that we will not do even the small
violence and and that's why i think
personally
how i can help the situation in
in ukraine and russia
what can i do in
arizona uh
and i think all of us
uh we can help
that situation that situation is coming
from all of us
uh it's not the fault of somebody in
ukraine it's not the fault of russian
it's coming from all of us it's the
fault of everybody
so
we planted those seeds
we created that war
and now we have choice uh
maybe we can stop it together
and i i think
if we
when we're doing our meditations uh we
every day every morning
uh just say today how can i
do less violence i already did my
meditation today i already
uh
stopped some small violence i was doing
to somebody i already took care of it
this morning and i think if we can do it
every morning
then
then we can change the seeds and this
situation
will change but
when you plant a scene it takes time to
grow and there's nobody in the universe
can make a seed grow in two hours or two
days
we we all have to
change our
personal behavior and and stop
doing small violence to other people and
then we have to dedicate the seed
uh to this problem in ukraine and russia
uh last thing for me
uh
i live in a very peaceful place
i don't have these problems uh
i have death problems
but i don't have a
attack problem or military problem uh
and and i have a good life and and i
have a
good income and i have good work
and
i think in a practical way
uh
in addition to changing our seeds
i think we have to work very very hard
with money
with support
to help the people who are suffering
in ukraine and uh already this
yesterday
uh our group here uh we we we know some
of the
people from ukraine who left ukraine
already they are already refugee
inside of europe and we are trying to
arrange for their housing
we are trying to rent places for them uh
we are sending money
uh we are contacting friends
in europe who can help them
uh find them place to stay and we are
offering to pay
and i think we all have to do something
like that even if it's only five dollars
or ten dollars but what money you have
if you have
ten thousand that's okay also
but uh we are
this small group in arizona you know we
are
taking responsibility uh to find them
place to stay
to support them financially
and help them to find a new life and a
new way to live
uh until things are peaceful again so i
think
of course we have to work with our seeds
uh
and that's the most important thing but
at the same time
all of us have to uh
find ways
to support now there's new refugees
maybe there will be a million refugees i
don't know
and then
we have the
power and we have the honor
to
to take care of them and to help them we
we have enough to eat here we have
enough money
we can we can share the money we have
and and we can help people in a really
a real way okay
uh politically
um
i think uh tension is very high
around the world
and uh
people are feeling very emotional even
in asia
uh if
even in america mexico south america
and i i don't think it's the time
and i don't think it will help
to blame other countries or to criticize
other countries it's not going to change
the situations you know i i don't think
it's
practical
uh
you know if i try to go to those
countries and criticize somebody or or
try to uh
express my anger
or blame somebody
you know
the lady in the kitchen she goes to the
bathroom
and she looks in the mirror and and
she sees who really caught the war in
the kitchen you know
so
uh i don't think it's a time to
criticize
our governments i i don't think it's the
time to
they it's not going to work i don't
think they will listen and
if we change our scenes
and we do everything we can do to help
people uh
i think that's practical and and i you
know i went to jail
during the vietnam war i went to jail
and i criticized the government
but i i don't think
that's the
most powerful
help we can do i think we have to
change our scenes
and then we all have
a chance to contribute and help
uh financially or or or help people find
a place to stay or things like something
peaceful
some peaceful way to help
uh last thing okay and then i'll open up
for questions
uh
there's a part in this letter
the fourth part
and uh there's a part in dci
uh which is
let me see what's the name of this
uh
yeah it's called seed
burning
bodies it means the
yeah no
there's an old uh joke
and
and i i'm sorry to say it's a little bit
naughty
uh
but uh
that's my stuff so anyway one guy is
just
sitting by the side of the road
you know in tibet
a long time ago like hundreds of years
ago
and uh
and he's meditating and some guy walking
down the road
and he saw this guy meditating you know
and he tap him on the shoulder you know
he says what are you doing you know
and the guy says i'm meditating you know
i'm a big meditator
and then the guy
tapped his shoulder again you know
he said what are you meditating
what's what's your topic what's your
meditation object
and the guys say uh i'm meditating on
on patience i'm i'm meditating how not
to get angry
and then the other guy said you know
what
i think you should just eat some
you know you should eat
you know and then that meditator got
very angry
and he jump up you know and he wants to
fight
and the other guy said okay bye
i'm just trying to help you with your
meditation you know
and he just walk away
so there's a there's a tantric way
to look at this problems when somebody
causes us a serious problem uh there's a
a tenta way diamond way
to to look at this person
that maybe they are buddha you know
maybe the guy
who says eat the guy who bothers
the other guy maybe he's a buddha you
know maybe he's trying to help him
with something and i think it doesn't
hurt
to remember
the possibility
that all this trouble is supposed to be
a real teaching for us
and maybe the troublemakers are
are really somebody special
uh trying to teach us something so i
know that's a very difficult
uh idea
i know
it's difficult to hold that idea
but in the end we have to
in the end it's the most powerful thing
we can do you know somebody
who loves us
has created this problem for us
uh so that we can grow
and we can learn to do the right thing
and we can learn not to
repay violence with violence yep
okay uh
those are my ideas and
uh seiji you got some questions for
grandpa
yeah thank you very much
for taking this time gesture
the first question actually
came yesterday
and the question is on one side we have
fear and anger towards the aggressor
on the other side we have
anger and hopelessness that we are the
aggressor
there's nothing much we can do
we don't agree with what is happening
but is there a way that we can truly
affect the situation as a group and not
just silently disagree and blame our
governments
yeah that's a that's a
i think that's the perfect question and
that's i guess that's the main question
today
and again uh i repeat uh i went to jail
i
you know during during my country's war
against vietnam
we a big group of us we went to jail we
fought the government
and uh
and
and my thinking has changed since those
days you know my thinking has gone
deeper
i understand more things
and i i really really understand
that
this is coming from me
uh
you know 10 000 miles away this is
coming from me
and i can stop it so i think this uh
when you feel angry in the kitchen you
know and by the way somebody asked me
my neighbor came to my house yesterday
and with her husband
and they said michael you know
we are always fighting
in our house you know can you give us
some advice you know
and i said uh
guess what me and veronica also fight
you know
sometimes
and uh
it's a human nature we we all do it you
know
after 50 years of meditation
uh geshe michael still get irritation on
his wife sometimes and she get irritated
with me
and uh
i think it's just important uh it
of course we have bad days of course we
make mistakes
of course we are frustrated
of course we would like to criticize the
government or we would like to
i got angry when i heard about this
yesterday i i was like oh
i'm gonna write a letter i'm gonna
tell the goddamn
uh politicians you know i'm gonna
then i realized every it's the same
thing as the husband in the kitchen it's
no different
uh
the fight in my family in the kitchen
and this big fight it's all the same
seeds i don't i i went to jail i did
that
i don't believe it will help i think uh
it's not the politician's fault
it's our fault it's it's we who plant
the seeds we planted this seas
and
if we can be a big family
which we are and i'm very very proud
of our russian-speaking
family
from all countries kazakhstan
kyrgyzstan
belarus
you know
all
ukraine russia we have
we have such a beautiful uh family
and they work so hard for many years now
to become a family and finally we are
family
and
and we are working together and and i
think
we are very powerful we are not a
country
but we are very powerful we
we know about this and and we can stop
this war
and we should stop this war and and this
is
this is why we're on this world just to
stop these things
that's our job
that's why we're here
so uh
let's work on our scenes yeah together
and it's it's not gonna be fixed by
politicians it's gonna be fixed by seeds
you know
i believe that
okay
cg
yeah thank you
um our next question
is
why do we get to see so many soldiers
going into war
even though probably everybody knows
that it's wrong
why do they have to do these things
against their beliefs
i'm thinking about these guys uh
it's my understanding that most of the
soldiers are are not volunteers they are
uh required
uh to go and fight um
and uh
i also was thinking about the same
question you know probably
the guys who are sent to fight they
don't really want to go
most of them i think 95 they don't want
to go when america was
hurting people in in afghanistan or
iraq or you know
i think most of those guys
they didn't want to go and and they did
everything to avoid going you know
and then finally they have to go and
they have families
they will get in trouble if they don't
go
you know
their families will suffer they will
suffer
i think most of them
the ones i know
who came out of the military
they are and my father
and veronica's father they were
very bad alcoholic
and they saw many people get killed and
they killed many people my father killed
many people
in the world war
veronica's father was in a bomber he
killed many people in europe
and uh when they came home uh they
became alcoholic and
they were violent also
and for the rest of their life uh they
their whole life was ruined
a whole generation
uh their happiness was ruined and so i
think uh
we have to remember that
most of these guys they don't want to
kill anybody
they would love to stay home in their
military base and have a nice dinner and
and
i think
when someone shoots a gun at you
and i've had a gun shot at me
it changes your life forever to to think
that one other person want to kill you
it it upset your mind for the rest of
your life you know
so to be a soldier on either side
and to meet somebody who wants to kill
you
it's a very
terrible terrible
change in your life
to have even one person want to kill you
so i i think we have to be
compassionate
to the soldiers also they they are just
doing what
their boss told them to do if they don't
do it
they will get big trouble
their families will get big trouble and
if they do do it
then the rest of their life is ruined
nobody can forget killing somebody
and
even if they never heard about uh the 10
good deeds
anybody who kills another person
they they never
recover they're emotionally
spiritually
even if they don't believe in religion
they never recover it's a terrible
terrible
they are victims they are the worst
victims so i think
we have to be
we have to show some compassion to those
guys they they are
trying to not get in trouble
and uh so i you know i think
we have to show some compassion to them
i i had a chance to meet the police who
arrested me
and that was very um interesting you
know they they also
they don't want to go out and hurt
people they they want to be home and
with their family and they want to eat a
nice dinner and have a quiet day and uh
so i think we have to have compassion
for these guys also yeah
okay stagey
the next question is
what seats should we plan to see
peace again and to deactivate the fear
in our hearts
yeah i think uh
what i mean what i'm doing personally
and that's after 50 years of training
you know
uh i know yesterday i started to
make a plan
of uh to check my own life
and see what kind of violence am i doing
you know and i found some small things
and some big things you know and
there's many kinds of violence
how we speak to other people is a kind
of violence
even how we think about other people
the thoughts we have about other people
can be a kind of uh violence
so i think uh
i mean
in my opinion after many years of
practice i think i have to
and i i was kind of
upset that
you know this war means uh
my own practice is not good or my own
practices
there's something wrong with my practice
and and i was pretty upset about that
and then
i thought well
let me check my life
there must be some kinds of violence i
am doing
that are not too obvious like maybe
maybe i do small violence
to people in how i talk to them
or uh my friend noor ibrahim who who
went through a terrible war in syria
uh she said uh in her experience
and she lived with the war there
for many years uh
she said uh this idea that
if i upset other people's mind so other
people's mind
is like a quiet lake
and
and if
when i meet them
if my mind is like a storm
like an ocean storm
and then i meet other people whose mind
is peaceful
then automatically when they get close
to me
i will upset their mind also so upset
mind
spreads like covid you know
when you're
feeling angry
or you are feeling upset
that attitude even with your face or
your gestures uh
it spreads to other people like kogan
you know and very
quickly and so
uh
nora was saying we had we met last night
with sejian noor and and um
we had dinner together and we were and
we're stanley and nelson we were
thinking uh
yeah we should try to
to check our own mind
and see if it's not
peaceful and it's angry and it's
upsetting other people
uh then if we watch our mind
and try to
try to take the upset away from other
people and not give them upset
uh i think that's a kind of non-violence
that's a hinsa
that's non-violence so i think uh
search your own life
and and don't stop after three days you
know the newspapers
they they will stop writing a lot about
ukraine in two weeks three weeks
the politicians know it
you know
the whole thing will
everybody will be suffering but the
newspaper will start to talk about
something else
and we
we have to
keep the
motivation to try to help you know we
have to
uh don't forget
uh the suffering that people have
sometimes the worst suffering is in the
next two three years
the suffering of the refugees long term
and
usually people help refugees in the
first three months two months and then
after that they forget and they think
think about
another netflix movie you know so
i think uh
we have to
be determined
uh to keep helping people long term and
that's what all is doing they are
they are helping refugees after 35 40
years they they are still helping them
and it takes it's the long term
it's a long term thing we have to do you
know we have to keep helping
cg
another question that came in is is
there something we can do as a group
that might be more powerful
than us doing things individually
i think it's a great question and i i do
believe that as a group like even today
what we're doing together is very
powerful
and i think
we can we can
share
i don't know why don't we try i'll make
a proposal maybe uh
let's let's do another uh meeting like
this
uh in the in the next week let's do
another meeting
and let's keep doing some meetings like
this and uh
i think if we all
make a
commitment
to do our meditation every day
and we make a commitment
to check what small violence i am doing
in my life
and then maybe next time we meet
together uh we can share
uh what kind of small violence did we
find
uh in our life and how did we stop it
how are we stopping it so maybe let's
have a meeting like that
and get together and talk about what
small violence did we find
uh in our own heart
and it can be like a big uh sojourn like
a big confession you know i i can talk
about my violence in my heart
and maybe in the next week let's meet
again
and
and all of us can talk about what we
found and in this way we can support
each other
and the seeds are much much more
powerful that's why uh monks and nuns
are required
to do sojung together twice a month yeah
like that
and and we'll send out a notice okay and
and we'll meet let's try to meet in in
the next five six days okay
and everybody check a small
violence in your heart
and then each of us can talk about what
we found and that way we can help each
other to
to get rid of those things yeah
sage good one more
yeah there is one question actually
related to what you just said
okay
you talk about violence against humans
but does violence against animals have
correlation with wars or for example
another question
ask
watching violent movies or violent
series
online does that
contribute to planting seeds to see this
uh
yeah
i mean yesterday uh
actually we're filming at the peachtree
cafe show
uh we are filming eight
tv shows it's like a netflix series
and uh
because i bought this cafe and and
unfortunately this cafe serve a lot of
meat
they serve pork
they serve beef
they serve
chicken
they serve turkey they serve
tuna fish
and now geisha has a problem you know if
i serve meat
then i'm helping to kill all those
animals and if i don't serve me
i nobody will come in this town in my
town nobody will come
so
we are having many many meetings uh
many hours of planning
uh of how to trick the
customer to eat no no meat
and how to stop using
animal products in the food and we are
actually doing many days of testing
uh how to remove the animal products
uh and trick the customer to
to eat something that doesn't kill
anything and um
yeah definitely
i think the colvin
because it it looks like it jumped from
animals to people in the
live animal markets
like the markets that sell uh live
monkeys or live birds
it looks like the virus jumped from
animals to humans and and i do believe
it's because we are killing animals and
especially we are removing their houses
every time we cut more
trees or we we ruin more forest
um
we are destroying their homes
and we don't think about it so in the
vinaya
you know we are translating these
ancient books of inaya
in it's a big big idea that uh
we shouldn't hurt the homes of the
animals in in for example among or none
uh we are not allowed to cut a living
tree
without a special ritual
if it's really really necessary we can
cut one
but otherwise we are not allowed to cut
a living tree because this is the home
of many animals you know and and uh
small
tiny animals so
i think it's very true uh if we can
stop this violence towards animals i
think we could uh
we could help a lot i often think i
think
that probably there's some
in the world
there's probably some country in the
past where people eat people you know
like i know there's such a thing
they they they they have a war
they kill the enemy and then they eat
them
you know and there is such a thing you
know in the past
and nowadays it seems very uh crazy to
us oh my god
you know
i mean if you go to american grocery
store
and you say i would like to have two
pounds of uh
human meat you know they will
they will go oh my god you're crazy you
know they don't say such a thing you
know
uh
and as the world becomes more civilized
you know as the world learns more about
seas i think uh
maybe 10 years 20 years from now
if you go to the store and you ask for
some cow meat or
chicken meat
maybe they will look at you like you're
crazy
so i think it's
i think it's possible and i think
i think uh
we are all doing this big big violence
that we
don't think about so let's all
i'm going to wrap up there cj i think
let's all think for a few days about the
seeds
the small seeds we have for violence oh
and about the movies
in the vinaya
we a monk and none we are not allowed to
go to a
a drama play they didn't have television
right they didn't have internet but
we are not supposed to go watch a a play
if they are killing people in the play
and of course it has a
it plants seeds in our minds and and i
i i grew up with a warm movie my dad was
in the war
he used to take us to the war movie he
used to play the warm movie music at
home
and
and then uh veronica look at me saying
this movie is violent let's let's leave
let's leave now
you know let's don't look at it you know
and uh
it's correct
and i also have this habit i from my
parents they used to watch the war
movies and i think uh
if we
we have the
you can always watch some romance or
or something like that you know there's
always something more
beautiful there's always something more
pleasant to watch so
we don't need the violent movie it
doesn't help us
it's not very
nice
and it doesn't hurt to just change the
channel and and i think watching movie
is good
sometimes it's a good relaxation i think
it's fine
but we have choice to watch something
more inspiring or something
some nice romance story or something
like that you know
uh
and and then we don't make those bad
seats
so seiji uh seiji will send out
uh invitation to you guys let's say
within the next five days
and you guys work for five days
on your small
violent seeds
and be ready to share with us guys you
know be ready to share with us guys
uh what did you find
and then maybe we can help each other
and i think if we
if we work as a team from all countries
[Music]
that's a beautiful uh
way to stop these things you know if we
work together
from all countries
and support each other this big seed
family i think we can stop this war yeah
i think so
let's try
let's try okay
all right seiji grandpa has to go to the
the peace treaty show
yes of course thank you very much for
taking time
yeah and thank you to all the
organizations something really cool that
happened
[Music]
all the organizations all the partners
came together in less than 24 hours so
yeah
i think it's a great legacy that you're
giving the world so thank you from on
behalf of all of us thank you for that
very cool and uh we'll send out a uh
invitation
so start checking your heart for small
seeds and
we can all share with each other
all right thank you very much and also i
mean uh
we have 12
world view organizations uh like aci dci
scim
diamond cutter classics
the directors
of each of the 12 organizations
yesterday
they committed
to find the financial support
uh for anyone
in the who's affected by this war so if
you know anybody
who needs help who needs financial help
to find a new place to stay
or they need food or they need medical
or
anything
the whole
world organization
uh
is is ready to support people
financially
and so please
let me know
let your local organizer know
and and we will help we will we make
this commitment it's a peaceful
commitment
uh that we will help anyone who needs
help
you know as far as we can financially we
we have
we can all sacrifice a little bit
uh to help these people who need us okay
all right so we're ready for you just
let us know
okay
all right
see you then
bye
okay